hello and welcome to the active
inference Institute this is actin guest
stream number
60.1 on October 18th
20123 today should be a great and very
exciting presentation and discussion
Kristen Whittle is here and we'll be
presenting on Reflections and
implications of a naive attitude to
architect cure there will be a
presentation followed by a discussion so
if you're watching live please feel free
to write any comments in the chat
otherwise thank you so much for joining
and really looking forward to this work
being
shared thank you Daniel um it's uh it's
a great pleasure being able to present
to you and uh your audience um and just
as we were maybe talking
the journey towards uh arriving here to
talk to you has been an very very
interesting one and one that's really
been undertaken since I was a young
person so
um it's it's thrilling and exciting to
be able to talk about the work that
we've been doing as a studio and kind of
seeing where the uh touch points and um
points of influence and interest to your
you and your audience um come into this
uh conversation about our sort of
artistic work I guess so what I wanted
to do is
to um
maybe explain what we're just about to
see uh before showing it um what it is
is a kind of an assemblage of work
that's been undertaken since I was
probably
22 um and and it it goes into a lot of
practical uh work that um has now been
completed um real large scale buildings
Etc so it's kind of part theoretical
part kind of trying to understand as a
curious person where I'm at and trying
to evolve a maybe a a strong systematic
view on architecture
because I guess the way I see it is that
architecture is is a bit lost um and and
in a sense there's an idea implicit in
the work which is
to kind of remind ourselves the purpose
of architecture in a kind of
pre-industrial form and then looking
towards the
future uh towards a very sophisticated
future that we we have in front of us
and trying to synchronize that with a
very humanist substrate humanist
philosophy um so um the reason why I
called the talk um uh a kind of
evocation about naive architect ET
actually comes back to some readings
that we've been doing uh that Carl Jung
uh evolved out of um readings that he'd
had uh from schilla the German uh writer
and philosopher
about
uh ways in which artistic production
occur so one would have for instance
one production of art step from an
natural source almost which he referred
to as
naive art and or a naive approach to Art
and the other which is what he referred
to as a Sentimental view or a
Sentimental approach which is more uh
that you're standing away from nature
and looking upon it and choosing which
direction to evolve in an objectifying
the direction
so the first thing to say is that our
work really stems from an extrapolation
of nature through our work in a kind of
intuitive instinctive manner um and then
maybe post rationalization or or more
theoretical Explorations after that but
the the very basics of it come from a
more intuitive approach and I think is
very
exciting um so the primary function is
this kind of relationship ship between a
human being and space so um having done
a lot of work in health uh become very
very interested in how the environment
affects
emotion um um and later on we'll sort of
be talking about how free energy and
coherence works with the brain and
things like this but but the essential
kind of exciting area is this
relationship between a human being
emotion feeling and space in the
environment and so our work is I guess
coming from a kind of slightly utopian
perspective seeking to
reconcile
um the maybe lack of connection in the
modern world to the physical environment
that's this kind of reward Matrix that
we that sits outside of our bodies um to
generate an architecture which is full
of meaning and nooks and hooks and
uh alos if you like emotional alos which
hook us into this kind of positive
feedback loop so we see our
extrapolation of our cognitive creative
processes being something to do with how
nature and feedback and cognition works
at a fundamental level so I'm very
interested in exploring this with you
and your audience later on is how
creativity is a sort of um manifestation
of cognition full
stop um so with architecture the
interesting thing about architecture is
it's really associated with other people
and it requires you to be an empath so
the big thing here is when you meet a
client who's got a problem you're really
trying to solve their problem and that
their problem is manifold in different
has different sort of Concepts with that
but I'm specifically interested in the
well-being aspect um of how they
themselves or their cohort that's um
living inside their buildings how they
behave and how well they feel uh once a
building's been built so architecture
extraverts and I guess through the
process of capturing the spirit of an
environment that's hopefully
regenerative um what we are now working
on is embodying that regenerative
philosophy into a kind of code which is
a complex code uh
interwoven um and made complex because
it's
fairly wide ranging and doesn't like
being in the boundaries of strict
philosophical guidelines if you know
what I mean it kind of ranges across
live data and and wanders around that
Matrix kind of freely the process of
embodiment is more to do with how the
process of experimentation and scoring
works at an intuitive level in order to
get very good uh architectural results
happening after that so essentially
interested in the Life journey and how
people grow and get nurtured over time
in their environments whether that's the
intimate environment of their personal
life their family lives or the
institutional lives that they
have um so without being kind of um
institutionalizing I'm interested in the
modularity if you like of people in the
way that their cognition behaviors work
at a sort of a neurobiological level I'm
interested in how idiosyncrasy comes
about within within that system and then
I'm interested and how those
idiosyncrasies can manifest into an
idiosyncratic architecture to to
basically create positive feedback
loops um so somehow within this there's
a
correlation between how cognition Works
which I see as the foundation to
creativity and then how the making
process works associated with that and
perfecting the making process and then
obviously what the lived experience of
those um environments is and then how
does that feedback work um to go back
into cognition and
creativity so um I guess some references
here might be useful
um the the work that smutz did you know
at the same time as when Yung was
working in
basle um trying to evolve a complex
holistic approach to the mind of body uh
has been in instrumental in the work
that we do um so in a sense uh one takes
that sort of expansive infinitely
expansive kind of perspective of the
universe being fed into us and then as
emitting that universe that sort of
overall large scale complex process
that's always happening somehow our
creative process is captured within that
so I iuse that as a bit of a reference
point um and I'd like to just I guess
put a a shout out here to to corbusier
because
um even though he he manifest a
scientific and
maybe um definitely
institutional um and scientific approach
to the modular the human modular his
Focus was really on the body um his
artistic maybe intuitive side was maybe
interested in the mind but the systems
and modernistic rationale that he
produced in the 20th century had a
massive effect on on cities globally and
ultimately kind of fell over post
brutalism into a kind of failure of
architecture I see the work that we're
doing is somehow an evolution of the
modula um and a much more comple
and um diverse manifestation of the
modul so um I guess coming back to car
young again um it would be necessary for
me to say that uh if you go along with
this story of naivity and processing
nature that one of those processes is to
do with the archetypal image and they're
sort of using the archetypal image as
some sort of foundation for the work so
if if this sort of stream of
Consciousness is available to you that's
one of the latching points of the work
and the question then becomes how do you
utilize that as a sort of febrile
substance to manifest new things so not
necessarily reproducing memory um as an
exact thing in and of itself it's more
associated with the creative utility of
the archetype as a substrate to tap into
and then applying different processes
onto that and because of that let's say
use of that substrate we're able to get
into a kind of deep uh relationship or a
deep conversation with the
public so um I think the reason why this
is kind of important at this moment in
time is you know the question about data
um what data informs architecture um
typically it's been ergonomic fact-based
information that's determined by spatial
mathematics um an ergonomic programming
of space
like
utility uh efficiency and those sorts of
Concepts um I'm sort of more interested
in the pre-industrial which is more to
do with scale um the idea of rooms the
idea of enclosure and and connect
uh
to other people um and and what sort of
spatial configurations allow for that um
so the question I have is really how do
we use data in that sense you know um
outside of the engineering based
mathematical scientific modernistic uh
platform for data so which I think
caused in institutionalization which has
been seen as a failure in architecture
and failure in society so we're sort of
we've never recovered really from the
failure of the institutionalization of
architecture so we're now at the point
with large data and AI to question what
gets assembled from here on in like and
how do we evolve something that's got
the Nuance complexity freedom of our
organic cell in in a kind of
artificialized
system so I'm very interested in
individuation both as a creative person
but also creating environments that
allow for other people to be
individuated and for that allowing that
ecosystem to
dominate so I'm therefore interested in
industrial experimentation or in
experimentalism and and how
um Mass customization can occur using um
new manufacturing techniques like you
know additive manufacturing for instance
um and in a sense democratizing the
design process to allow everyone to be
an artist to be an
architect but anyway um so to kind of
unpack what we would do
typically um is rather than go on a
linear Journey which is a fact-based
re reduced simplistic architectural
Journey like a plus b equals c we go on
a circular kind of coiling Journey uh
it's certainly moving forward but
information's coming in from different
Vantage points continually throughout
the process and I guess we've we've
ended up being very efficient at this um
but it allows us to have kind of
oppositional trajectories coming into
the design Journey it allows us to see
things objectively as well as
subjectively using qualitative and
quantitative information and Building
Things and destroying things on a
journey of creation so things die
certain things live the living things
get tested and might die and it evolves
in that sort of way okay
so um if you're looking at maybe the
definitions of
creativity um it would probably Center
on how creative processes end up
creating new things like
um it's not so just speak about
mimicking it's about creating new things
that have a function and I guess from
our
perspective this coiling process is the
foundation to that um invention process
um where somehow you yourself because
you yourself have connected into that
information process that by necessity
what comes out of it um traps uh the
exter external world into that internal
world and gets affected by that Journey
so it's sort of a trap uh for for for
society um but the main objective is for
um one to achieve what I would call
coherence which is um which definitely
comes back to free energy and active
inference where you can
essentially map and see the world moving
forward in a coherent way latch onto it
and for it to feed back meaning and
reward into your life and therefore
extend you
know longevity and improve livability
those sorts of
things so
um by sort of going in that direction
what what we need to do is to kind of
assess what The Well of knowledge uh
Plus
memory uh plus
ambition what what sort of constitutes
that domain so what we've done in our
own way is to
assemble uh trajectories and kind of
taxonomy a working taxonomy that ranges
between social and political principles
to Scientific and artist and
technological principles and art and
Architectural principles and that
essentially forms a kind of rosette
which we've called deep learning and
that's a kind of foundation that has
existed for me since childhood and
obviously is a dynamic assembly process
so that's the kind of scaffold and then
if you imagine taking that living
scaffold to a project we then
um create a dynamic relationship uh
between that scaffold to a client and
the projections and information that we
get to and from a client as well as to
from a site so a site would for instance
constitute how where the sun moves how
it moves around a site where the wind
blows what's the Ecology of the site
um and in a city what are its neighbors
what's the social um backdrop to a
site and it's also about people
obviously and it's about monitoring and
assessing people and how they are coming
and going within within our sites um
curtilage so you're sort of assembling
that very Broad and complex picture that
essentially forms that nugget of Truth
which we've defined as feeling so we
trust our feelings about about a sight
now it sounds naive talking about
feelings in architecture and there's no
sort of um I don't believe there's any
sort of academic construct that's been
developed around feelings um it's been
sort of chipped away in in naist
principles Po in postmodernist theory
but um the idea of a feeling is is
obviously if you're trusting your
instincts is a very
complex
um model of of truth that's a truth to
you and so if if you were able to form
a um a layered understanding about how
that feeling is constructed you're then
able to uh
I guess talk about it openly with your
studio and with your clients and start
utilizing it and testing it more
pragmatically
um so what we've done is
to um is to then layer that out from
initiation phases all the way through
schematic delivery and post occupancy
phases of projects so it's is so that
feel concept is the Nugget that
everything is tested against and so when
when we get to the end of the process uh
we're measuring against what that
original feeling was and asking question
does it feel like what we felt like At
the beginning how does it differ and how
what do other people think about that
feeling and I guess it's probably
important for me to say the Curiosity
that underpins all of this uh started
because the work that was happening
ended up being very well fitted to the
client's prerogatives and I would have a
situation quite commonly where a client
would say to me how did you read my mind
like how were you able to comprehend
what our needs were when it there was a
lot of unspoken truth about a
project um how were you able
to encapsulate what our desires were in
a project how is that possible and or in
the sense in the hospital why does the
hospital feel right why does it feel
good why is it restorative like how have
you been able to achieve that and
because of these questions that came at
me I decided back in 2019 to study it to
work out why it was happening what fed
it what underpinned so that's kind of
what why I'm here really talking to you
Daniel um and I guess what I've realized
is that um that the the perception model
that I've just talked about in terms of
feeling um it has obviously coroller or
an association with memory and
anticipation so projection and somehow
in a very complex um neur neurological
process we're capturing that data and
then we're able to project it into
architectural models so if you imagine
cognition Pro like intuitive cognition
projecting scenarios to help guide your
body through space what I do as an
architect is I actually make models of
that projection and I then test those
models in order to get the perfect model
the thing that's the most coherent model
for me and for the the situation so it's
a situationally specific cerent model
that's what I'm searching for and that's
what I build at the end of the day so
it's based on feedback so we would call
that an embodied holistic code for
architecture okay so it's based on the
idea that we are all modular people in
the sense that the foundation for us all
our neurobiological foundations are
common um before they become
ideosyncratic so to speak um and I'm
sure you'll correct me on all that um
so anyway so but it's fair to say that
we are all living beings right and we we
have all of these um normal
instinctive kind of primitively
derived things that we do in life and
this is what unifies us so as an
architect it's important for me to know
how these
actions uh work because they actually
underpin how the functioning capacity
for building works
but it's also true to say that in the
work we are trying to reduce anxiety not
invoke anxiety we're trying to create uh
Harmony rather than invoke uh complexity
to the to the point that it creates neur
U pathologies we we're trying to Harmon
harmonize our existence in cities
specifically and in contemporary cities
this is where we go drastic wrong
because the human being is never at the
center of the
conversation uh with regards to a
development it's always a spreadsheet
driven exercise and this is where we go
wrong so our work begins with studying
uh how this works how this kind of human
environment works these are cting
hollers uh art piece
uh this kind of objectifying the social
domain of a restaurant
which is very evocative but as a basic
process and this is again humble me with
an iPhone what I try to do all the time
every day is to document what I would
call
Nooks uh where people are settling and
where people are seeking to settle in
certain domains whether that's to
socialize or to have the sort of
intimate moments of uh self-reflection
how do we move through
cities so what I'm always doing is
photographing um basically cities and
people and that forms the
foundation so I call that
um and again this is a very unacademic
terminology learn dwell
no so I've I've worked out
that my fascination with photographing
these things stems from the fact that I
I'm learning something from what I'm
looking at and that's why I'm drawn to
them and then also it's conflated with
the idea that I want to live in that
environment so there's there's something
about the domain that's on photographing
that combines and conflates learning
something and living in somewhere that's
going to be good for me so it's a
compilation of those two things so our
work's very much about the assemblage
and collecting of that rationalized
domain of live dwell no
uh so we're always fascinated with how
mattera for instance assembles itself so
this is um an aerial photograph of a
region of Northern Victoria a desert
region of Northern Victoria which um
defines this um it's an irrigation
colony called
mjur which um is a desert region that
became an an agricultural agrarian
society that was all to do with growing
um food food for the city of Melbourne
and but but if you look at it from on
top you get to see the literal
translation of those ecosystems being
played out by the patterns of nature so
it's the patterns of nature that we're
interested in here we're interested in
how
um we sanctify our existence through
symbolic constructs this again goes back
to the archetypes we're interested in
materials that are deep understanding
about the kind of
exacting expression of nature uh this is
we have some fascinating trees in
in Victoria in Australia and um I became
fascinated in trees when I did The Royal
Children's Hospital um there always a
foundation pillar for me
anyway um materials that maybe are
transformative materials that are
ambiguous uh especially drawn to those
sorts of materials um materials that
have maybe
a
handcrafted and slightly
Sublime complex process that's created
them um materials that have used literal
tree trunks in buildings that maybe have
an unusually primitive quality to
them as well as highly elaborate
expressions of ress and thresholds that
we see In classical architecture or
humble um quiet domains that have a an
atmosphere of living
dwelling um there a sort of livingness
to an environment so I'm interesting
these subtleties and then amplifying
those subtleties in architecture the
idea of intimacy and privacy in the
public domain Nooks of a a doorway
entry or this um
I guess almost cinematic memory uh
that's embedded into
cities um the organic growth of cities
the bricolage of cities how growth
happens with different personalities and
how they form organic
constructs or basic symbolic archetypal
classical City
terminology um like here in pizzza in it
in in
Italy
um and and also the organic um
scaled midcal cities that you see in
Europe that have
Consolidated that intimate relationship
to space solid and void and creating um
spatial conru constructs where you have
external rooms and internal rooms and
the idea of those spaces aggregating
social activity so all of those things
are overall Fascinations and I put them
in because they are just long-term
fascinations which are always being
recorded it's a kind of like a
background noise but so the origins of
the work um go back to Sak I think when
I was studying in Sak in Switzerland in
America um where I think I was
fascinated by the idea of
coexisting realities in structures so I
call this the hyper realism of Life
reality
okay so this for instance is a
sculptural piece that I did um about um
creating a new construction out of an
old construction so uh looking at how an
old building's column and beam structure
was working and how um The Association
of the original thought of that
structure which was used the drawings if
you like the drawings were the perfect
model of that structure then you have
the
actualized construction which is
slightly different than the idealized
one and then you have maybe the course
of time and organic processes changing
that structure and then of course you
have your your memory and projection uh
that's that's pushed onto that when you
experience it so this idea of having an
assemblage of all of those realities
made material into a structure I became
fascinated by that in order to form a
trer basis for architecture so that's
kind of like back in um the early 90s
and then that sort of morphed into
looking at architecture more like a body
so looking at the more um organic
substrate of architecture being much s
more similar to a body um and looking at
how a molding process around the body
and create a replicatable architecture
so sort of in a sense A Primitive
version of a data fed architectural
model being built as a modular system
but replicating more of a kind of bodily
expression so forming a very intimate
relationship between body architecture
and making a very
ambiguous um relationship there rather
than a a sort of um inside outside or
dualistic relationship this is much more
blurred
um so that that I guess indicates maybe
an
artistic and curious mind being played
out as a young architect and then fast
forward that into reality into
professional work um I started to work
um back in 20072 2008 in in healthcare
projects and this was one of my first
projects um uh it was it's for the most
acute
um Hair Center for mental health
patients in the kind of lower
socioeconomic District of Melbourne
called dandong and what we assembled
here is an idea of deinstitutionalizing
a mental health hospital by using the
house as the model for the building and
assembling essentially those was like
about 30 houses around different
Courtyard spaces and making everything
out of primarily recycled Timber
and then changing the relationship
between the building and the people
inside but also the people inside the
building and the public so
deinstitutionalizing all of those
relationships and
normalizing those sorts of things where
people would probably walk past the
building and think it was a health Spar
or some I don't know Health hotel but in
fact it's actually treating the most
acutely in need patients inside
and then using the courtyards as a kind
of natural oasis to feed positive energy
into those people okay so there's that
these buildings
are um are closed in and around
Courtyard spaces that focuses the energy
towards the
courtyard and each Courtyard is
designated differently and that sort of
relationship is more like a Closter so
it's more like a kind of classical
Closter monastic Closter where peace of
mind and mindfulness comes about through
that focus and on that singular um place
of peace right so we using here
materiality um nature that's somehow
getting in between the building and the
footpath and then the focus of nature on
the inside to re assign the
relationships between those people's um
Minds in and themselves but also their
minds in relation to the outside
world so these are how these sketches
and ideas got translated into
spaces that change the more hard-edged
relationship of buildings to Nature uh
private realm to public realm into much
more of a
harmonized uh fluid sequential
picturesque sequences of space where
we're able to bring in a more what I
would call a soft Fascination rather
than a hard fascination reality for
those people inside the building
um so you can see for instance the
almost beach-like environment around the
building that that forms the border the
framing of the building before you get
to the actual public realm so it's a
kind of like an imposition of raw nature
raw Bush into the public realm that
helps to harmonize these people and and
another project that came about slightly
later was a very um prestigious
physicist in in Melbourne who needed to
have a domain where he could work and
and do his algorithms his uh
experimentation
and he had a space that was in a very
urbanized environment on a on a very
harsh Street Edge so we created a
cabin uh for him in the city in a
shop um so essentially um one had I
don't know whether you can see my cursor
but there was a sort of Street on the
bottom edge of this image this is the
plan of how we built it um there was a
street on the bottom edge with a lot of
passing traffic and people and and in
order to kind of recalibrate the space
so that it worked to generate positive
regenerative um environment for him we
entered from the back and we arranged a
sequence of Entry spaces that
essentially blackbox
experiences that would um kind of
launder the urban fog or the urban pain
of the city the hard fascination of the
city launder that out of his body before
coming into this Timber domain where he
would rebuild and Connect into the truth
that was the overall kind of existential
phenomenological Journey that we were
setting so as we walking into the space
we were walking through
these deep um kind of lost spaces that
were all black with a scrunchy kind of
um um Floor Covering different Acoustics
and then you would go through this door
towards the light it would open up to
you and you'd be bathed in this kind of
warm light where each of the Timber
elements was retained its organic
[Music]
you
know wabby saabi esque
character and you know it worked such a
it worked so well for him he's never
kind of
um
uh I mean he's always been extremely
supportive of the fact that I did this
for him because he was kind of it proved
to me that on a oneto one level if you
listen to someone's needs you can then
create an environment that has a major
effect on them
psychologically
um okay and then part of the journey and
this is part of the kind of rational um
trajectory of the work we worked with a
very uh preeminent company called BHP
bullettin it's the world's largest
Mining Company to do their headquarters
in Melbourne and in this project we were
able
to change the relationship between how a
corporate office worked in a city and
how the relation ship between in a sense
an institutionalized corporate entity
and the foot path the streetcape and the
history could coevolve so
that what's typically a very dry
and alienating environment could somehow
evoke the past the memory of a place and
create a different material reality and
material
associations for everyone who uses the
building and this project sat on an old
site that used to be a
theater um and it sat in the district of
the city that used to be a manufacturing
District so they used to make fancy
Goods like they used to make jewelry and
watches and things like this so what we
wanted the building to be is some sort
of Jewel like
project um that spoke about that and and
sort of heroz that history we brought
that into the space construct that
linked the two streets that bounded the
site and we created this kind of
sequential Journey that detuned people
from the busyness into the
quietness um through the use of natural
materials and you can see here at the
back of the site how the warehouse
District gets mapped into the structure
and embedded in a slightly different way
using cut glass to make it more
ceremonial and
exotic and that's how the project kind
of sits in the city and you can see the
Echoes of the relationship between the
the
gothic uh there's a river also sits down
here so there's somehow a relationship
between the
environment the gothic the river and the
past all sort of assembled into an
architectural approach that's specific
to that side
um in terms of residential work um we
also been working on um some very
interesting um Edge conditions in the
city of Melbourne where we've been able
to explore the the tall building um
typology and how tall buildings can work
as Civic
buildings um and this is an edge of the
city where lots of parades have happened
in the past uh edged by Parkland
old buildings that were built uh in the
sort of mid 1800s using
Stone and so what we were keen on doing
here is establish an a new architecture
that's away from the glass curtain wall
driven
um way of making things and return the
city back to heavy
materiality and extruding what would
normally be a Palo scale midscale
building into a taller building so that
essentially your
physical uh experience of the public
realm was in about continuity but then
also the expression of the building on
the skyline because cities are seen from
afar our city here is a big city in a
very flat on it's one of the world's
largest Bassel planes so it sort of
erupts out of that Bassel plane so
buildings can seem can be seen from afar
we wanted to Signal what the city was
about from a
distance uh using a different approach
and then connected into this sort of
edge condition of the city so you're
very much taking part in the activation
of streets and the definition of Street
edges and seeing architecture more as a
kind of
passive um tool for containing space and
defining
Edge um but then also uh creating a
Nooks uh in this case kind of cave like
Nooks around the edge of the building
where you feel the weight of the city
around
you this is a photograph of how that
edge condition
works um so embodiment I perhaps go back
to this embodiment is more
about uh and I guess what I'm trying to
establish here is sometimes you're
trying to rationalize from memory and
from a kind of fact based almost like a
simple trajectory to create a building
other times you're trying to capture an
emotion that's perhaps more complex and
evasive um so I call this process more
like
embodiment and this is um process that
we use for the new Australian Embassy
which is just being finished in
Washington DC just about to be opened
where we were looking at how material
like copper can establish itself as
the material to denote a
country and the experiences of that
material in the city of Washington which
has a
very um sort of
ceremonial and hard to grasp
institutional reality and to kind of
insert something that was more open
deinstitutionalized
welcoming and also textured in such a
way that it drew or created meaning for
people outside of the building but also
as you come into the building what those
experiences are where of about Australia
so we we're looking very much in drawing
experiences in plan
form and then using the copper to evoke
this
mysterious uh
acology of of Australia that's
particularly evident in the ephemeral uh
Salt Lakes that you see in the desert
regions so if you ever fly over
Australia it's just the most
beguiling experience that you'll never
forget and it was trying to establish a
dialogue with that for people in
Washington um that's a picture of on top
of all Ruru and you get to see the kind
of
monumental modular monumentality of
that and we wanted to establish
something that was kind of rock like or
big and bulky and solid and then insert
these fishes into it and these are some
of those
sketches so this is again
um it's interesting kind of working
remote from another city and inserting a
piece of a country's DNA into another
city but here we're kind of looking at
the dimension the the dimensional
reality of the building and how texture
can get worked into a building from
outside to
inside and how nature can establish
itself in different ways different
experiences so breaking down the form of
the building and then we started to look
at because we had to What machines and
Technology would be able to produce the
material that we wanted so we actually
get into uh how the heating of the
copper would work and how we would
create kind of organic replication so a
a process of making material that has a
lot of idiosyncrasy associated with it
but that's
replicatable so we use this heating
machine a top- down heating machine
which the um material will be rolled
through and it established this
polychromatic kind of burnt finish uh
within which we had a just an infinite
amount of variegation very
beautiful so this whole process evolved
around the the making of the building
around using that polychromatic finish
to create
um an echo of Australia on the outside
of the building that would stay silent
but
beguiling um and then the way that those
different panels were used was to create
a kind of inflection and that inflection
that we had on the facade was coming
through from The rhythms of the forests
that
interspersed in the desert and that was
kind of mapped onto these
sequences onto the building which then
became kind of fractionalized and more
granular the closer you got to the
building and we would study that in
virtual reality now because we're able
to and you're able to add the
environment around it so you're able to
choose your charm of day all those
finishes
and you have a much more closed loop
reality when you're designing now that
can get very much close to the finished
position the finished state in advance
so you're able to have a much more
exacting feedback loop design system to
embed those feelings and emotions into a
structure and get it right so this is
the kind of flickering and ambiguous
layering that I was trying to talk about
earlier in an natural Forest uh eucalyp
Forest in the High
Country and then that would come into
the workplace environment through a
sequence of um there's two atriums that
are collocated one's a public Atrium
one's a private Atrium the private
Atrium is a hub for all of the different
disciplines in in an embassy to come
together and so what we're trying to
create here is um it's all made out of
Timber and that Timber is being used to
infuse the environment with with an
association with Australia in particular
the light the striated light and the raw
Timber working together and the spatial
sequence being kind of open and
expansive and tall like a eucalyp tree
so eucalyp tree is super tall has a big
open canopy and it has this small Leaf
kind of delicate light that comes
through it so all of those feelings
we're trying to trap into a workplace
setting that we know both
symbolizes Australia but also is healthy
for people inside the building so this
is about healthy workplace philosophy
being used as a ceremonial gateway to
Australia and these are the further
images of that and that's has its
currently stands just about to be
opened and that's the copper um standing
five blocks north of the White House um
as a sort of um edifice of Australia in
Washington
um so as I guess we were developing
um a human focused approach we also you
can't escape your responsibilities to
the environment planetar speaking so we
also worked with aspects of the circular
economy and looking at
how um a temporary building can can
utilize wood in the form of paper
so we created an artwork stroke building
a temporary museum for the National
Gallery of Victoria in a competition
entry
which um looked at making a Timber
modular Gallery with paper rooms running
through it so the paper which is
obviously traditionally been used as a
as a an element that you would draw on
or paint on but in this case the paper
is used as a building material so the
building material itself is or the space
itself is the
canvas and because of its translucent
nature we were looking at how the
environment around the building would
map on to those spaces so in a sense
what you're walking into is a
spatial immersive spatial experience of
the environment moving around the room
through the you know the sun's movements
mapping different realities whether it
be trees or the framing of the building
into that room and for that environment
to uh change over time so with the rain
and the Sun the actual degradation of
that environment would also be present
in the environment and then also we were
able to infuse the um we used to use
primitive days in Australia
the glue that comes out of eucalyp trees
to combine with Ash to create a kind of
cement so the idea of using those
different natural glues to create smells
ukp smell for instance is used as an
antiseptic um you can use
um a paper uh material like a kind of
sponge that can emit um smells and and
um
[Music]
um almost create a kind of natural
outdoor environment
inside you know what I mean so we we
were interested in developing those
naturalized experiences in cubic
spaces um and then basically collapsing
the whole building and recycling it
making it into a book that was the whole
concept so it's a popup building that
was made into eventually a book
we've also been working in
um in Asia this is a project we did in
South Korea two years ago and this is a
um an embodiment project where we
essentially
understood this is in Soul um that the
city of soul is like 80% of South Korea
is made out of granite uh mountains so
it's a very mountainous country but soul
is in a kind of Delta
so but it's surrounded by these Granite
monolithic Hills and the hills are used
to to for people to escape the city so
they go up the hill the mountain and
they see a different future they see a
different life they get connected to
Nature and then they go back into the
urban realm so what this project was
about is
encapsulating that natural getaway type
space but bringing it into the city to
change the dialogue about what a city
could be in the future so we we would
let's say decode those sorts of things
and apply it to personality types
whether it be a company personality type
or an
individual we
decoded process of how those mountains
came into being and how the
um geometry of those kind of geod like
um I think they're called tour
structures how they would have they're
formed and how they've been ceremonial
lied and celebrated through Korean art
through Asian art you know the
whole idiosyncrasy of a piece of
beautiful piece of stone or piece of
wood and also it's I didn't know this at
the time but seler is also the world
center for these um Neolithic structures
which in fact uh were hollowed out and
used as primitive buildings primitive
um um ceremonial places let's call them
um so this relationship between the
landscape and the identity the cultural
identity of South Korea as seen through
this ge geological construct being made
into an office building that provided
this health benefit so how did those
Health experiences work on a hillside
walking up and how could we translate
those experiences into a building so we
we having absorbed all of that we would
then go into sketch mode and track that
geometry and communicate that geometry
into
plans and into
elevations and then into experiences of
how you would approach a building what
does it look like at night as well as
daytime how does the ground plane car
parking roadway work with the
Subterranean retail
how does the how do all these
relationships work if you follow that
that
geometry to create a holistic kind of
social Tower
construct uh that's kind of living
version of the mountain brought into the
City and you know in terms of breakout
spaces um this especially relevant
today when we have a question mark about
work and about what an office building
is um what we're trying to say here that
an office building isn't focused
necessarily about work and it's
certainly not home it's something else
and the something else thing is this
sort of natural experience or place of
elation place of Joy where you go to to
get enlightened so the idea of the
building being a kind of tool for
enlightenment to generate
better ideas more Progressive ideas and
using nature to achieve that those links
so that's what all this is about it's
about sort
of well in some sense it's sentimental
but it's it's TR having gone through the
process of embodying those physical
experiences on site trips that we did
and photographing that and studying the
cultural identity it's then allowing us
to then create that Matrix of
experiences into a
form which go top to bottom across the
building and form a different dialogue
with the public
realm so very much a building that
changes throughout the
day and forms different dialogue now in
terms of formulas and I think formulas
are very relevant topic the first
Formula that we put together was for the
new Royal Children's Hospital here in
Melbourne 2007 which was opened by the
queen
where instead of um let's
say forming a kind
of
um a a sort of what I call it an
artificial uh Accord with the children
who were being
um dealt with within the within the
environment of the roal Children's
Hospital we saw them really as small
adults as opposed to children so we saw
them as sophisticated
uh people just like adults so so so the
first issue was to not create a language
for the building that was going to be
somehow derogatory or form a a
poor a poor support structure a poor
support scaffold for the children so we
wanted a sophisticated structure that
could again
elaborate that internal world of the
child um think about
how illness Works in children who are
stuck in their beds for say a month
bedbound and institutionalized and and
that sort of fearful relationship
between doctor patient patient in big
billion dollar Hospital change all of
those relationships so that it's no
longer an institution but a place where
you again not at home you're not in a
hospital you're somewhere else it's
you're in a place of Enlightenment and
it's that enlight M which improves your
health and restores your
energies so seeing children differently
than what we're told to think of
children as being these sophisticated
creatures that are curious about the
world and assembling cognitive
cognitively assembling their world every
day just like we are and forming
identities in the same way so we sort of
created a what might be called the first
health code salutogenic health code for
hospital and we didn't just use the
salutogenic concepts that came from
Aaron antonovsky which are all about
coherence we B
in um concepts of evidence-based design
which stem from Roger ol's work on
natural light and then looking onto
nature the kaplan's work on self
festination and nature and their
concepts of attention restoration Theory
and we we looked into Reg schools in
Italy and we perhaps added another two
or three concepts on top of that and we
used the assemblage of Blended formulas
to create the hospital so it's not
strictly about either evidence-based
design or salutogenic it's about an
assembly or
diversity um but essentially we're
creating an environment that was made
into an adaptable building but the
environment was the was the driver and
the en
environment was there to form an escape
from habitual activities and that would
form a kind of soft interface a soft and
reflective interface that would retain
your attention
effortlessly so this is all
about kind
of capturing a quality in a building
that is very similar to the qualities
that you would have walking through a
park where you're continually drawn into
detailed
areas and where you see the movement of
light and air and the general ecology as
a living environment surrounding you um
and washing through you so the idea of
having a kind of soft washing of a soft
environment how do you go about making a
hospital out of that so we systematize
that this is just a diagram of how the
salutogenic process works in terms of
building coherence from
the the focus on building intimate
spaces as well as public spaces as well
as family spaces changing the
relationship between how care goes from
being you going to the care to the care
going to you so the model of care here
is about doctors and nurses and the
Health Care system going to the child
not the other way around um so it's it's
complex in of it self and that was a
major tool for how we designed the
building but then we're always cognizant
of
the natural nourishment that we get from
natural light natural air currents uh
pointing the for instance this the
building towards the Sun so we embedded
the Cadian Rhythm into the building and
essentially made a building that was
very similar to Forest therapy um by
mapping the journey through a path
and translating that into a building we
would naturally have a good environment
for people to be in so so this is the
first time that we're really starting to
focus on the pathways between the mind
and the environment and how it changes
our
hormonal uh structures or how it affects
our central nervous system Etc to
produce positivistic results so this
kind of linking between the environment
and the body the mind and the body and
architecture for the first time was a
established for us so in terms of
intuition the idea was to we had an
urban edge condition but a fabulous Park
that we designed the building into so we
what we were seeking to do is to push
the building and migrate the building
into the park migrate Urban form to
point it towards the Sun so that the the
building ended up pointing due north and
by doing that we're able to create um um
Parkland around the majority of the
building
um and then what we were doing is
embedding through drawing experiences of
that parking setting onto the outside of
the building and through experiences of
entering and walking through the
building and then focusing in on the
child in the bed and what their own
experiences of selft Fascination could
be within that environment to make sure
they're restored as best as possible so
we created effectively a model of
salutogenesis
into a building this is a $1.2 billion
project it had two and a half thousand
rooms inside this
building and we were dealing with all
ages because it had researchers you know
doctors nurses researches there all ages
focused around children who would start
their journey within their old
Children's Hospital as babies and
perhaps still be going there as adults
so we had to deal with all of the age
groups in the building this is just a
focus on how the night and daytime use
of the building Works in relation to
Nature the celebration the historical
cultural celebration of nature in it's
kind of picturesque Australia naturally
picturesque um it's like a country
garden and using those features in the
building this is a picture of that
picturesque landscape in Victoria this
is our site uh before it was built on it
used to be a cricket pitch and the
cricket pitch points due north
interestingly points due north and that
became where we put our street and we
created a street that would form the the
Central Social connection device through
the
building um so this was us
mapping uh qualities
visceral uh
textural uh warm and inviting qualities
of the park before we designed so we're
studying the park studying how
the layers of soft fasination work how
Shadows
work what's the sort of geometry of a
tree what's the that that sort of
strange ergonomic quality of the trees
how they cluster together what sort of
light comes through a tree how does a
bark texture work and what's the toneal
quality of that
tree so all of this was documented
before we started to design
and then we were embedding those
experiences
into
circumstances uh we developed up a color
palette out of that we created um walls
that that reflected the kind of layered
sof
festination light quality of the park we
went into great detail this is a almost
like a onetoone study of an edge of
glass and how dots and patterns and soft
curves were being used to evoke that and
then we created a bunch of experiences
throughout all of the two and a half
thousand rooms that evoke that those
experiences into
architecture principally on the basis
that the relationship between you as a
person looking out into nature was a
healthy one and nature was brought to
life through the Sun and what we're
essentially doing is trapping the Sun
nature energy and bringing that into the
building that was the essential
relationship and then we were
personalizing it so avoiding
institutionalized replication we were
interested in having each of the two and
a half thousand rooms different to one
another as well which is pretty high
order of
complexity uh this is the plan of the
impatient unit which was shaped as an
organic star shape uh for practical
functional reasons but because we did
that we're able to break the experiences
of the nurse station relationships with
the children into smaller packets of
space uh so and then we were able to
open up the corridors into Collective
space rather than Corridor space to make
more of a home and a kind of focus point
for for the different spaces so I guess
what I'm trying to say without going
into great detail is that within each of
the spaces either at a very microscopic
detailed material matter perspective or
spatially speaking how rooms relate to
corridors or how a building relates to a
park all of those the different scales
they were all treated with the same
level of
care um it's again focus is on um again
associated with soft desination how this
kind of dot matrix that was encircling
the building how it resonated with the
eyes and how it would change with time
of day that would come to life we used
energy saving techniques to surround the
building with these glazed Sun Canopies
that
were that were made out of colored glass
made out of dots of different colors and
different shapes and because we're able
to map the trees outside into the space
the and because we're making the Sun
cannabies out of glass we're able to
create a kind of transcendent experience
of the edge of the building that was
bringing that energy deep into the heart
of where the children were living and
this is how the external building came
about so we're literally translating the
foreground of Nature and wrapping it
into the building to form a blurred
relationship between building and
Landscape so it's very firmly embedded
into the landscape it's an extrapolation
of the
landscape so in terms of the geometry um
it started with the tree geometry and
you can see this in the shadows but then
if you look at those kind of arms that
are coming out of the tree we wanted to
utilize that geometry for um how we
constructed the larger spaces whether it
be waiting spaces or the bridges that
that or the textures u in the internal
cladding of how these um yeah bridges
that that that came in and out of the
different fun functional areas of the
building would crisscross the street and
how they would assemble themselves into
these kind of Nooks or torsion
sculptures that were very similar to the
outside
world so whether it's an area of
compression or a concept
about the scale of an object like the
scale of a bridge or the scale of a of a
of a staircase how those large scale
pieces would relate to a CH child's
Mind's Eye in even though you're in a
large space these large scale pieces
were being assembled to kind of
deinstitutionalized but also form a
sympathetic relationship to a to to the
scale of a child and the joy of a
child's Mind's
Eye and on the outside just looking at
how these sun shades again would
replicate
um pattern language of the
trees into a kind of
foliage that changed color and patina
depending on the time of
day so that was kind of very
interesting process and it after I guess
we finished it it
um it changed my Paradigm or changed my
thinking of of architecture as being a
tool for health full start
so since then since
2007 all of the work that I've been
doing has been Associated health and
seeing cities as generators for health
um and so once you once you get to that
position you then start to think well is
nature or our job in translating nature
all associated with the natural world
like a royal park and using software
ation or is it something that's more
associated with human psychology and the
nature of Being Human and I guess the
latter concept uh came into being kind
of more recently with uh work that we're
again doing in South Korea which we
called trans
buildings which are less simple
translations of nature which actually
focus more on human nature in buildings
and this project was in Ean
and it was a project for
a a private members club and you would
probably know Soho house and uh
buildings of such like in big cities
where members come together in private
Realms to celebrate being flate members
um what we were doing here is changing
that Paradigm and forming a private
members club that was much more
public um so unpacking a singular
building and making into a kind of Civic
domain so creating public space out of a
private building and then in a in the
site forming a different relationship
between buildings in their environment
um making a more ambiguous
relationship um so the buildings were
seen as
sculptures and kind of like non-b
buildings
um they were they were broken down into
pieces so it became a district as
opposed to a
building and what we were trying to do
again is to change the psychological
relationship between the people inside
the building and the building itself but
also the members of the public who are
looking onto the building and forming a
questioning relationship so kind of
eming a an existential crisis if you
know mean so seeing a building as being
a partner in the Journey of existence in
the crisis of existence and the
questioning of
existence um and not necessarily being a
Utopia but being kind of just a living
piece of city and we're also interested
in how the new world of virtual reality
is coming into being so trying to
establish a building that can go into
the metaverse as well so we collocated
the idea of a new virtual building with
an existing building to form a more
hyperreal
um form of architecture which I'll come
on to perhaps later in the conversation
but the environment was a very
interesting uh context where we had the
most International District of
Soul a place uh fraught with social uh
friction um a disheveled environment
that was very popular came to life at
night so a lot of kind of non-liable
features in in very broad sense um that
naturally come about in cities and
embracing that rather than critiquing it
but trying to form very beautiful
cinematic environments which were highly
evocative making buildings that were
charged with a kind of psychological
tension using materials that were hard
to describe
so in this case it was 3D printed
wood and seeing the building as an
outside
face but having an in a completely
different internal world so sort of in a
sense evoking what we're like as people
we have an external appearance but we
have a highly complex and changing
internal world forming similar
relationships in a building and then
making a building that was ambiguous as
to what it looked like
having gone through
um an interest in in uh this essay by JG
Ballard his his fabulous uh written
piece on the garden of time we then
started
to don't have time to go into that but
we then got into translating all of that
into art
pieces which then came into physical
experiences of the
buildings um disappearing underground
and the exploration of an underground
world so essentially arriving at an
assemblage of buildings half of which
are above ground half which are below
ground appearing as
these concrete simple Prismatic
volumes and quite Stern and
monolithic and using water to at the
base of the building to cleanse the
buildings and the
environment to then looking at how the
internal World worked as a more
organic
place and contary to the Prismatic
volumes on the outside looking at a much
more bodily like sequence of spaces on
the
inside so whether you're arriving at the
retail or the the rooms within the
private club or arriving by car you're
sort of arriving inside a body and
having a very different relationship and
then the Two Worlds then connected and
we started to look at how Windows worked
in the building how the concrete would
reduce to fabric would would transcend
and change into glass and how different
relationships were working through
different spaces and how that would
become organically
expressed into different sorts of
thresholds which were more more body
type thresholds to form a building that
was kind of half building half
body and then looking at how the
concrete in the evening would then
recede back to become a more translucent
material so the idea of the buildings
kind of being more
translucent during the night time and
solid during the daytime
and having that ephemeral
quality and now lastly uh we've been
working on the new hydrogen economy in
South Australia in a place called W
looking how to use new materials like
green
steel how to repurpose industrial
buildings but looking at how principally
the
ecosystem how the industrial
ecosystem uh can create a more more
humanized uh Urban world so we've got
we're on the edge here of looking at how
the urban reality of this new city
that's going to grow because of hydrogen
energy how the relationship
between energy the
Earth manufacturing and urbanization
triangulate into a more holistic
Paradigm by looking at all of the
different ecosystems being embedded into
one another so starting with nature
and the natural reality of the site the
Ecology of the
site um how that the ecology has been
manifest into structures whether it be
Timber Old Timber peers or old existing
buildings into a kind of embedded memory
of of the
site so we're recording in a sense what
the memory the cultural
ecological memory is of the site and
then We're translating that into to a
shaped language an experiential language
that then overlays into the new housing
project that we're doing to generate
experiences that capture those that that
sort of existing experience and
manifesting into a bolder bigger
identity for the city so these are
sketches as they translate into new
house so sort of balance between the
sculptural world of found objects on a
beach made into to a piece of
architecture um forming a new city out
of all of those embedded
memories so so I guess Daniel and and
the audience if we've got any audience
left all that um what what all of that
constitutes is a kind of flow and the
reason why I presented to you like that
is it represents a kind of intellectual
theoretical practical artistic flow that
represents how creative cognition works
and I guess the overall ambition is that
because of that coiling process we end
up with a much more coherent and
friendly human celebratory world and
that's a world that we all need and
deserve wow I guess I would have said
I'm not sure where the spiral ends but
of course it doesn't
end yeah it doesn't end absolutely yeah
well please
continue and well I I mean from my
perspective I've I see the
institutionalization of the world of
architecture the world of property
development the world of law the world
of Politics the world of Industry
um having behaved poorly let's say in
the past or per perhaps narcissistically
speaking um
evolving systems that serve their own
ends in their own ways but we're now
sort of in an environment where we can
actually bring all of those pieces
together and to form a
self-reinforcing self-re
improving you know Networks
and thoughts and processes that can
actually inform and and and manifest a
better physical world so it does mean
that as a artist architect you are
interested in politics you are
interested in Industry you are
interested in AI for
instance um because you're interested in
consilience you're interested in tying
together the different disciplines just
like and how Works you're in dialogue
with the
environment so in a sense all of this is
is naive in the sense that all that is
is a replication of natural
process it was an incredible
presentation and I have many pages of
notes but first to kind of lead into
that I would love to hear about your
engagements and encounters with Carl
friston at all
um well like here um I went through a
very
similar um kind of presentation and I
guess what was interesting I didn't know
how it would resonate or whether it
would whether it was just me fantasizing
that it had something to do with free
energy and active inference but I had a
very strong hunch that it did and I
guess what I'm what I got from it that
it very very much indeed does correlate
very strongly with the embedded
principles that Carl's works all about
and um I think he was very pleased uh to
see it being translated in this
discipline in this way
um and I felt relieved to be to be quite
honest you Daniel talking to someone of
the statring caliber of someone someone
like Carl um to be able to talk
directly with him and and the people
around him who are all excellent um was
was was extremely fascinating and
beautiful um I mean I see it as a kind
of the the way I I just see it as the
way forward um and I'm excited just to
understand how it
can translate into into a process in a
way not in
able to encapsulate the complexity
logically so that people can understand
can get on board so we can de
institutionalize this this logic and
spread the word if you know what I mean
um spread it around and encourage
participation and
experimentation
um so I got I got the kind of if if
you're not to mean the collapse of
boundaries in the in the conversation
with Carl
because because it can go into all areas
of course it goes into all areas I'm
just showing how it
translates in the way I do it but
[Music]
um I think it it needs a long time to
kind of just sit there and and
discussions to to to to Spring from here
you know to
Spring to get going um I see this
spinning into all sorts of different
areas so I mean at the moment we're
looking
at how to utilize this in coding terms
so I'm interested in computation and
statistics I'm interested in urbanism
like making new cities um so how we
translate this into we're building a
$200 billion new rail loop around the
city of Melbourne how this can translate
into new districts and new cities and
how we can break down
this typical artificial boundary between
new
things
and I don't know new cities which are
typically unfriendly unloved and
unwanted into being
coveted people aspiring to move move
into these things right and we never got
that right ever um I mean since Paris
you know we've never got it right so the
idea is to actually is to get something
finally up and running which represents
an opportunity to to do something at a
regional level a local cultural
Community level that per perpetrates
Evolution at different scales in
different areas through a
process kind of Open
Source very fascinating again there's
there's so many places that I want to
just touch on because I I think you do
present so many contact points and ways
of expressing that will resonate with
active inference
enthusiasts and yeah I I guess the
starting point is the learn dwell Nook
so you were taking those measurements
because they were informative you were
updating your cognitive model from your
sensory input and that changed your
generative model it also may have been
actionable information it may have been
folded through an iterated realized
process back into the design and then
fundamentally that's an attracting space
it's an attractor or a dwell space just
like if you had a landscape and you were
shaking up the a ball on the landscape
it would dwell as you turn down the
temperature and slow down the shaking it
would dwell
probabilistically according to the
features of that landscape and that
concept of attractor points attracting
sets and then also wandering sets and
moving yes Nooks which is something that
may be able to happen in a digital space
or it might be a mobile element or
movement is all just a question of over
what time frame that idea of the
attracting set and of things exist
by virtue of what their attracting set
is that's the heart of the free energy
principle so starting with the dwell on
a surface and then I'm sure there must
be a point in the design where it's like
so we saw 50% this and 50% that do we
want to carry that forward or are we
looking for like 8020 or do we want 40
4020 with a new affordance being
introduced through through landscape
modification it completely fluently um
touches on it and I just love that
learned well photography because I think
probably many of us with cameras in hand
now have our own little peculiar brand
of Photography and then what does that
say about us yes what Daniel what do you
think about this whole
um world that that s in terms of free
energy active inference and how
cognition works
in relation to creative process creative
cognitive process as let's say creative
cognitive process being a kind of
symbolic representation of cognitive
process as a sort of exploration as a
projection what do you think about
that well we may have to revisit it
multiple times but here's what I wrote
down perhaps touching on it you showed
a image of of a photograph of some metal
that reflected the idealized and the
actualized construction of the
ibeam coming together yes and that both
of them had differences that were uh
materialized differences through time
and weathering and context and it was an
assemblage so there was like all of this
richness and I thought wow it's an ibeam
that's like the self that's like the eye
and then there's a comparison of the
idealized eye even of just a proximately
idealized eye like I could be standing
up right now or I could pick up that
object that kind of idealized
counterfactual adjacent possible the
abductive the associative the creative
that exists in our lional proximity of
the eye and
yeah and then it's all about that what
the image that was shown with
this sometimes horrific but sometimes
beautiful ju deposition of the real and
the actual eye or moving it a little bit
out of psychology like the real and the
actual self model and then our
calibrator on that is variational free
energy yeah
but you know this kind
of how do you say it
um uh the concept of
the the talk was about naive
architecture or naive approach which is
a kind of you as vessel for that
complexity so you're sort of living
manifestation of that
complexity as a person person as a human
being you're not you know I'm not a tree
I'm not a plant I'm a human being but
that cognitive
process and natural biology and The
Coincidence of those two
realities being brought together as a
cognitive process that manifests that
expression of the well it's the it's
sort of the first Loop is you absorbing
and then expressing and then the
expression becomes the physical
manifestation of that thought process
being the substrate that you live in
right so that whole chur chilian concept
of you know buildings
make you know we make buildings building
make us that whole loop
system um you know it's obviously
been been proven to be to be right and
cities can either be pathogenic or
sologenic you
know how many cities in today's world in
modern sense are salutogenic cities
nonone you know you go you'd have to go
back to the Villages and towns and blah
blah blah which which are very
much um tight manifestations of humanity
in in a sense in a physical
manifestation sense um and the
abstracted I would call it Excel
spreadsheet logic where you take one
element and then extrapolate cities out
of that one element loses all of that
Nuance so now being in a situation where
we understand that nuance and we
understand the importance of that
Nuance there are elements but also links
in that Nuance Matrix that we can almost
calibrate and we can we we can capture
them we can embody them we can recreate
them and now we've got this kind of
opportunity within that sort of
febr Matrix of stuff that's in part
facts that are math-based facts in part
just
visual U Reflections or actual
photographs
um but we're now able to kind of like
bring all of that together as a sort of
more complex arrangement of
things to manifest something as the new
paradigm
um that forms that sort of partner in in
our cognitive
process uh that's not an enemy to our
cognitive process that forms the
coherence and the um natural it's our
natural place if you're not mean it's
the sort of
hiiga space it's the place of
dwelling yeah a lot of angles it's the
William Blake dialectic Songs of
Innocence songs of experience but I want
to connect again the visual
representation what what do these visual
what what even are we looking at it's
something I asked myself probably on
2third of the slides I was like is this
if there wasn't a person in the frame I
was like yeah is this a microscope is it
VR is this aerial footage and sometimes
probably even if then later on oh that's
four trees but it's like but is it and
all of that richness of of the the
temporally thick interpretive process
and also the relationship between like
the synchronous Audio Visual and the I
secades a lot of other features that we
can quantify um there was a scale
freeness or a scale ambiguity a system
ambiguity and the mathematics of active
inference and the free energy principle
are scale free or we could SK say scale
friendly which is to say they don't host
or hinge on any specific or particular
system or scale it's not a framework
about brains but it can be used to paint
or Express models of brains and so that
meta
theoretical position which may have more
resonance with the creative encounter or
the kind of like massively collaborative
and Global projects that you described
that setting from a practice angle
especially with augmented and synthetic
intelligence may come to be closer to
the process of active inference modeling
than 1995 or 2015 writing a statistics
program yeah I think so I I'm with you
on that I think it is I think it's
really it's kind of
experimental actual
experimentation of of the free energy
the world of free energy and the
successes of it we can see and
experience um that's the joy of it and I
think I also would like to say that with
studying how
creative process works you're almost
peing inside free energy as well I mean
I this is just me talking and I don't
know teally speaking whether I'm right
on this or not but it just feels to me
that it's a rich source
of um information to unpack that
actually could provide some really good
strong direction for the
future the the piece that really left an
impression on me that makes me think you
you said right there the successes the
realiz successes
successes only in principle or
hypothetical the real ones are real and
you mentioned in the
copper for the Washington DC building
that you wanted to make it idiosyncratic
yet
reproducible and that's like the magic
quadrant like yeah we have Technologies
of reproducibility without idiosyn
criticity plus
externality Plus aect
um path pathology
Etc and so this quadrant or space with
the idiosyncratic and reproducible and
then it was like it's a top- down
heating
machine and so in some ways the realized
material
artifact becomes like The Crucible or
the eye of the needle where the
generative process the process that
leads to the artifact's deposition
um or acction or however it's built it's
a demonstration of the sense making and
the Aesthetics and the technical
capacity it's like wow they brought that
rock from here to here and then yeah did
they do it this way or that way and
people
today discuss and debate how did they do
that building how did they do that
building and so it's like the archetypal
Logistics operational setting
construction physical Construction
ruction is the tip of the iceberg of the
physical and informational supply chain
and all of those for those who have the
generative models to see we look at the
Obelisk from Rome and that is like a big
rock and it ripples for those who have
knowledge of that
setting but also the footprints of an
animal to another animal or the phermone
of one ant nest made to another ant mate
or all these other like infinite last
miles and those are all yes ANS with
each
other they're not in contradiction to
each other and neither is it a
contradiction to have a unified way to
discuss and approach
that yeah so so within your work and
within the studies of act active
inference how are you critiquing or
unpacking modernity in cities in
buildings how is that being how is the
world of active inference being explored
in the physical domain or is it or is it
being explored or but when it is being
explored
how sophisticated or or longterm has the
research
been all great questions the first thing
that came to mind is that there's been
some work on the affective and the
physiological and the
interceptive and while there has been
for example models of movement within a
maze to
really get to the point of a a simulated
model being more than just an intuition
pump which can be more than enough
itself but for it to be more than that
really at this point in time requires a
a team professional effort that to the
few extents it is happening is probably
happening in proprietary settings but we
do everything we can to highlight the
open source
capacities and the kinds of models that
people are building I think one setting
that is pointed to a lot but also has
not received that much empirical or
open-source work is like
like ecosystems of shared
intelligence instead of just talking
about the physicality of the internet of
things or iot or everything in that
space being able to integrate the
spatial and the ergonomic like you
pointed to earlier with efforts to
provide something like a meter stick but
we're not just looking for distance we
want something to calibrate the
construction or the architecture process
and at hand was the Industrial or
potentially modern system and then what
I saw right from the beginning of the
presentation was like a yearning for a
compliment or a juxtapose or the shadow
of that
and affective cognitive science now
being able to kind of square that Circle
or however you want to think about that
where it's like well we
could organize our project around
people's sense of narrative
fulfillment and that could have
disastrous ecological consequence so
let's care about the narrative and the
ecological okay but then the business
might not exist all right bring it into
the generative
model what El what do people think about
what we have now and that must iterate
that must be
Intermodal and so that allows the imbu
of all these different aspects that that
for me were evoked when you talked about
like soft attention whereas in science
and technology and math which was only
onethird of your threepiece
pie a soft
attention can be a
boon for a beginner in scoping at the
space it can also be um a pleasure and a
tool for an expert who's able to have a
soft background and then sharpen
attention um but to be useful one has to
be on the other side of that innocence
and
experience and that's a
tough learning
curve because there's and no one is ever
going to be able to have all of the hard
attentional regimes there're just too
many it's just like trying to know every
language or like know it's like it
doesn't even make sense it's not even
preferable like for any number of
reasons and then it's like well so what
do we do but it's like but there we are
scratching our heads talking about how
we're going to create living re and make
it work
physiologically if not far far more than
physiologically a as a group as a team
as probably discussions have always
happened leading through to the
inculturated
and lovable structures that we
love and
so I love I love how you use words spr
is fantastic um
um see I would sort of say that
diversity that one is enabl to get hold
of to grab in and bring in to a creative
process if you have a porous or agile
process allows you to bring anything in
think always made me feel as though when
a project came about I would always say
well there's a million buildings here
which one do we want to to build which
one do we want to design and that was
kind of a fairly alien concept to a lot
of people in my industry or in my
education certainly people wouldn't W
talking those terms because it had
always been trapped by some cultural
doctrine that one had to be a
postmodernist one had to be a
deconstructive
a regionalist a modernist a this or a
that there was always some sort of
virtuous um theoretical underpinning to
something that was determining what you
it were basically
institutionalizing what things should be
like for for whatever reason for power
influence money whatever it is we were
trapping a process thing um codifying it
and then telling everyone that they had
to be in that box whereas what we're
talking about now is totally liberated
it's totally free for being what it it
should be so my yearning for craft my
yearning for vernacular
architecture my yearning for that hard
to describe soft granular environment
that I like so much in the old world in
inverted commers or or seen in agrarian
structures um
I can now talk about in terms of how
professionals talk to one another how
teams are made how
um the intangible has now become sort of
tangible through the ability of talking
about it in terms of free energy um
Neuroscience it's enabled us to actually
bridge the gap between qualitative and
quantitative and that's the joy of it of
being able to go from an artist
wondering in the bull rushes feeling
utopian but creative and curious
manifesting things to really having a
quantifiable opinion about something and
being able to capture it
compartmentalizing it without losing the
nuances compart compartmentalizing it
and explaining it to someone and then
you know it should be like sort of
engaging someone to design your house
quite often what would happen you'd end
up with arguments with your ARG
you'd then something end up with
something that you didn't want um You
probably went through some sort of mood
board analysis or gave him some sort of
brief or them some sort of brief um but
there's always been this hard boundary
between what you want as a person and
what someone else is giving to you you
know and I I think what this is enabling
is a
soft
um uh
sort of navigation or translation or
um Arbitrage this sort of soft and
giving Arbitrage between you and the
environment you and someone else you and
a large corporation that enables both
parties to come together around a common
set of values that enables that
negotiation of that Arbitrage to work in
everyone's interests so I think what
sits on benath all of this it's
translating yet into an architectural
placemaking philosophy and place being a
kind
of maybe closely associated with
coherence I would say but anyway the
idea of it being a negotiation tool I
love that I love the
environment as being an expression of
fruitful coherent Arbitrage of
relationships
awesome and synchrony generalized
synchrony with the environment not lock
step with the environment but synchrony
like turn-taking and meaningful dialogue
and alignment with our environment our
built environment information
architectures our social architectures
and and I think this is something that
hopefully we'll see unfold in so many
different ways is like how do we hold
the moment like the aesthetic moment the
lived
[Music]
um The Humble home environment moment or
whatever moment the affective moment
outside or or even before we even
quantify the affective or the cognitive
like the
real Primal moment and it's like maybe
one day we'll have tools soft enough to
touch I don't think we have them today
so what is one thing that we can do and
maybe not even regret ever looking back
something like create a buffer or a
container for the vital
moment and so it's like let's let's just
make sure everyone's at the workshop on
time and that this is the way that they
like it and and all these features and
be very thoughtful and mindful and value
aligned up to the moment of The Craft
and and then if there's more to say it
may be right to say it and impose then
and constrain then but if there's
nothing more to say after you've like
brought everyone to the
dance then that would also be
fine and so then the challenge is like
but you have to make a building like
you're being paid for a building and
then there has to be that received
public or Civic
experience that is not like oh we'll
watch this two-hour live stream and
check out this or that analytical
framework there has to be the real
direct and and I mean those are the
kinds
of knots and Tangles that it's just
amazing to hear your your journey and
your way
around the kind of I call them I call
I've just written this down actually a
Nook machine I think what what I do is
like Nook
machines and
so I think by helping the World by
creating Nook
machines we end up
generating a more truthful honest
coherent
Amplified truthful kind of expression of
how we want to live with all of the
different
instincts activities that we do every
day right and it's kind of like the
enabling of all of those activities
whether we want personalized in you know
intimate moments or expressive outward
moments but the health of a human being
being that sort of inner and outer World
being being enabled to effortlessly
assemble every day U Melodies and that's
sort of idea of a building let's say an
environment capturing a multitude of
different feelings not a singular
feeling but a a mul multitude of layered
feelings to create Melodies and
so often what happens in symbolic
architectures you're really drilling
down in the guard reals of a singular
emotive reality and you know none of us
live in that singular motive
reality and we don't want to live in a
single modality like that so that sort
of multiplicity of modalities sets that
that sort of complex
Melody thing
and I think that's that's what we're
really talking about is through that
communal process or that
iterative
self-improving process which absorbs
contrasts and works through just
positions we can absorb a country's
voice
uh a complex singular voice into another
person's voice and the beauty is that
synchronicity or that moment being
distilled which then enables further
conversations to happen which is kind of
what I think nature does to us naturally
it sort of forms
that dialogue um and what we're missing
out of cities is and the physical
environment is a lack of dialogue
capacity so this Nook machine thing is
really about creating paracity a living
paracity that that allows people to be
okay to be people you know because we
the city in a sense is telling people
that they can't be themselves and that
can't be good for it can't be good for
us you
know
so I think we're getting close to kind
of having a kind of complex modeling
process that then can feed from data
that we can find that's say
to improve the
modeling but you know we're on a journey
of course but we're at the point in time
where we can
probably get a lot closer right now in
objective terms in rational terms to get
that poetic feeling distilled and to be
able to tweak it to be able to sort of
play with it tweak it synthesize
differently sounds and the music coming
from it before we build something and
then we also can start
measuring those qualities after after
it's been made and literally feed back
that information to the next
project wow well in our sort of
closing is thoughts a close synonym for
Nook is also Niche like I've heard a
breakfast Niche and in Ecology of course
we talk about different aspects of the
Niche and in cognitive Science 2 the
Developmental and the cognitive Niche
and so it's like that's the map in the
territory the cognitive Niche is where
your belief distribution is hanging out
and there's a cognitive Niche about the
breakfast nook like we ought to have
breakfast there or we're the kind of
family that uses the breakfast nook for
that but it's like whatever it is on the
map
and whatever it is on the territory with
the of
course digital being a complexifying
factor in all of this but whatever it is
let's just go with that and have a path
of least action on the generative model
active inference with a free energy
principle and then we can talk about
what we expect and what we prefer like
we expect everybody for breakfast at
exactly this time versus like we have
loose expectations or it could be
uniform across the whole day we can talk
about our expectations and
preferences no appeal to a reward people
aren't loitering and lounging in the
park for a reward function directly or
per and yet that is what the kind of
Quantified
Matrix and the reinforcement and the
reward learning which is not wrong
it's just a special case it's a
partial constrained expression and a
partial constrained
regime on all sides of the
blanket and
so I don't know where it all goes from
there but Daniel you know the the
learning dwelling Nook concept the
conflation of having a
synchronous um let's say density of
want where you're both intrigued and
curious about something but also kind of
want to be in it so you're sort of
learning you you as you're moving
through the environment you're seeking
to
learn and on top of that you're seeking
to gain and arguably seeking to inhabit
or dwell better or improve your chance
of dwelling better um as some sort of
effective strategy for survival yeah I
don't know whether that's true but it
it's quite actually the two components
of expected free energy you said to
learn and to gain epistemic value
pragmatic value these are the two
components of a unified imperative and
we want a high reliability setting where
it's like you're not here to learn we
need this done that way
yeah and then there's also the other end
of the pool and there's all the Dynamics
and movements within and it's like
that's that's the pallet now what do we
want to
say
yeah yeah um and what what needs to be
said comes out of the the arbitraging
process uh which goes into a lot of
detail because doing a building for
instance takes like seven to 10 years
sometimes you know know it's not a short
process
um and the reality is that they're kind
of like codes it's like you're building
an algorithm it's just it's a physical
algorithm it's a physical embodiment of
knowledge and that
knowledge creates physical experience
that people intuitively experience
without you know maybe dwelling on the
seriousness of it or the impact of it
people are at least experiencing it and
so this the trouble that architecture
has always had in the modern era is
evaluating the power of architecture or
the meaning of architecture to health
and wellbeing and the growth of culture
why why is architecture important is it
important um and if it is important how
do we quantify the importance of it
um and and Architects and the industry
tend to if they're
not maybe born into environments where
they naturally get it
if you're born outside of architecture
in a sense maybe you've been surrounded
by industrial reality the whole of your
entire life you may not I'm I'm just
guessing here but you may not fully
comprehend at a bodily
level what the meaning of that is and
why it's important virtuous beneficial I
don't know
but but for Me intuitively Maybe This
goes back to
archetypes being an artist
architect looking
to looking and being curious is is a
foundational thing for me at a personal
level personality type level but so is
the idea of creating structure so the
idea of creating on one hand and the
idea of structure on the other so
creating
scaffolds and so um that's my particular
personality type
um and I feel as though it's almost my
job you know it's like I've been born to
do a job and I'm enacting that job I'm
just trying to unpack what I would
naturally urge what I've been naturally
urging to do my entire life uh to the
point
where um if someone says why does this
space feel so good
it's it's much more complex than just
saying well it's got good natural light
or or um the Acoustics are good or it
functions really well there's the
density of the psychological reality
that people never get to talk about and
there's never really been a framing of
that I mean hiig has had a good Bach
heiger have had a stabed it um but it
hasn't had the sort
of um
balance um
of dealing with highs and lows the
different tonality of Life uh the naive
to the sophisticated the the poetic to
the I don't know the everyday there's
never really been something that
systematically drawn all of those
constituent elements together and it's
always become a dry dried up kind of
artifact a dried up almost
purposeless lacking purpose Theory
that sort of begins and ends and then
it's just there on a
bookshelf for other people to learn
about but there's never really been an
active
philosophy that has translated and
improved continuously over time and
there's something about
neurobiology and the fact that it
Bridges bridges into creativity in the
physical environment that is the kind of
for me it's the
um it's it's everything really it's the
it's it's the moment this is the moment
when it actually comes together and
we're able to actually use these kind of
Golden
Threads and make make some magic and
that magic not being some sort of um
accident but actually having a tangible
realizable teachable
or open sourceable kind of reality to it
we're ju we're just at that moment I
think where we can begin that
work thank you would you like to make
any closing statements and then I'll
make a closing
statement
um I I think this first of a lot of
conversations I just think this is the
primer for me it's the primer so watch
this
space thank you you I hope so this was
unique in multiple ways and a delightful
experience and and a real journey and
I'll close because you invoked a golden
string with the quotation that William
Blake had on his
Tombstone
constructed he wrote I give you the end
of a golden string only wind it into a
ball it will lead you in at Heaven's
Gate built in Jerusalem's
wall very nice very ni thank you till
number
60.2 yes till next time it's been
awesome thank you thank you see you bye
bye e